Guide to the C. Ray Smith Manuscript and Research Files on the Yale Art and Architecture Building by Paul Rudolph
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
C. Ray Smith manuscript and research files on the Yale Art and Architecture Building by Paul Rudolph
1953-2008
1960-1981
MS 1948
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.94
(37 boxes)
The collection includes correspondence, research notes, recorded interviews and interview transcripts, and drafts of C. Ray Smith's unpublished manuscript, entitled The Biography of a Building: Paul Rudolph's Art and Architecture Building at Yale. It also includes site and structural information about the building itself, as well as a questionnaire for Yale School of Architecture alumni, designed by Smith, regarding their impressions of the building.
Smith, C. Ray
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of S. Sinclair Smith, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
C. Ray Smith was an architectural writer and critic based in New York City. He received a master's degree in architecture from Yale in 1958. He authored several books on architecture and design, and was an editor of many prominent architectural publications, including Progressive Architecture, Interiors, and Oculus. He died in 1988.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence, research notes, recorded interviews and interview transcripts, and drafts of C. Ray Smith's unpublished manuscript, entitled The Biography of a Building: Paul Rudolph's Art and Architecture Building at Yale. It also includes site and structural information about the building itself, as well as a questionnaire for Yale School of Architecture alumni, designed by Smith, regarding their impressions of the building. Some materials in the collection have sustained water damage.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by type of material.
Rudolph, Paul, 1918-1997; Smith, C. Ray; Yale Art and Architecture Building (New Haven, Conn.)
- The Biography of a Building: Paul Rudolph's Art and Architecture Building at Yale
  Scope and Contents
  Unpublished manuscript by C. Ray Smith. Interview transcripts are likely to be related to the interviews on audiocassette.
  - Academy for Educational Development fellowship application and award information, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annotated typescript draft and research notes, 1964-circa 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Annotated typescript draft, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence and interview transcripts, Circa 1981-2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and other material relating to publication, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interview transcripts, Circa 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - Research files and notes, Circa 1957-1980 (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
  - Research note cards, Circa 1957-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rudolph, Paul, interview transcripts and related correspondence, Circa 1981-2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Interviews with architects and others affiliated with the construction of the Art and Architecture Building
  The interviews with architects and others affiliated with the construction of the Art and Architecture Building consist of audiocassettes recorded by Smith. The labels on the cassettes were handwritten by Smith and are occasionally illegible. Labels are transcribed as written, with notations by the archivist, where applicable, in brackets. Where two dates for a cassette are listed, the first indicates the date of side 1, followed by the date of side 2.
  Arrangement
  Contents of the audiocassettes are listed in alphabetical order by label on side 1.
  General note
  See also: transcripts of interviews located with other materials on Smith's The Biography of a Building manuscript.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Baker, Jim [sides 1 and 2], Circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 3)
  - Bedford, Bill [side 1], Der Scutt [side 2], 1981 April 7; 1 audiocassette (Box 4)
  - C + O #3 (continues w/1977 Nov 30) [side 1], Rudolph [side 2], 1977 November 23, 1978 February 15; 1 (Box 5)
  - Chaet, Bernard side 2 / Dunn [side 1], Chaet 1 [side 2], Circa 1978; 1 (Box 6)
  - Chermayeff, Serge (not re A&A) + Louis Finkelstein [side 1], Finkelstein / Engman [side 2], 1978 May 17, 1978 May 18; 1 audiocassette (Box 7)
  - Close, Chuck / Abbot Tor / [Cesar] Pelli [side 1], Pelli / [Fumihiko] Maki / [Tokeyama?], Circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 8)
  - Danes 2 [side 1], New Haven / Frank [Zamecanti?] [side 2], 1981 June 4, 1981 April 23; 1 (Box 9)
  - Dunn 2 [side 1], Lytle / CRS & Shepherd, Santora [side 2], Circa 1978; 1 (Box 10)
  - Engman / [Kissivoff?] already transd / C & G [side 1], C & G transcribed already / Chuck Close [side 2], Circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 11)
    Label indicates recorded on May 24-25, but does not indicate year.
  - Franzen, Ulrich re. Rudolph [side 1], [side 2 unlabeled], Circa 1978; 1 (Box 12)
  - Geismar, Tom, already transcribed [side 1], Lyden 2 [side 2], 1979 October 11; 1 audiocassette (Box 13)
  - Griswold, [A. Whitney] MS / MS Tilson [side 1], MS Tilson [side 2], 1979 November 7, 1979 November 8; 1 (Box 14)
  - Helmsley, Harry (do not transcribe) [side 1], Danes 1 [side 2], 1979 January 12, 1981 April 4; 1 audiocassette (Box 15)
  - Lyden [side 1], Dave Hummel 1 [side 2], Circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 16)
  - Miller, J. Irwin [side 1], [side 2 label erased], 1979 November 7; 1 audiocassette (Box 17)
  - Moore, Charles Willard on A&A [sides 1 and 2], 1980 November 5; 1 (Box 18)
  - Netsch [sides 1 and 2], Circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 19)
  - Osborn, Robert & Jane Ritchie & Elodie Osborn [sides 1 & 2], 1980 March 30; 1 audiocassette (Box 20)
  - Rudolph [sides 1 and 2], 1977 December 22-28; 1 audiocassette (Box 21)
  - [Rudolph, Paul Marvin] PMR [side 1], [side 2 not labeled], Circa 1978; 1 (Box 22)
  - [Rudolph, Paul Marvin] PMR [side 1], [side 2 not labeled], Circa 1978; 1 (Box 23)
  - Rudolph [sides 1 and 2], 1978 February 9; 1 audiocassette (Box 24)
  - Rudolph discussion of book (begin transcribing) [sides 1 and 2], 1978 February 27; 1 (Box 25)
  - Rudolph [side 1], [side 2 information crossed out], 1978 March 15; 1 (Box 26)
  - Rudolph [side 1], [side 2 information crossed out], 1978 March 29; 1 audiocassette (Box 27)
  - Rudolph [side 1], [side 2 not labeled], 1979 December 28; 1 audiocassette (Box 28)
  - Sabro (cont'd), De Cossy 1 [side 1], De Cossy 2, Spiegel, Richard Shadford [side 2], Circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 29)
  - Shadford (cont'd) [side 1], Shadford (conc) [side 2], Circa 1978; 1 (Box 30)
  - Silvestri - Bldg inspctr [side 1], [side 2 not labeled], Circa 1978; 1 (Box 31)
  - Solomon 1 [side 1], 2 [side 2], Circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 32)
  - Solomon 3 [side 1], 4 [side 2], Circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 33)
  - Stern, RAM [side 1], [side 2 not labeled], Circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 34)
  - Tworkov & Froeberg [side 1], Froeberg [side 2], Circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 35)
  - Wardlaw, George [side 1], do not transcribe [side 2], 1979 July 2; 1 audiocassette (Box 36)
  - Welliver, Neil [side 1], Attitude-Meaning (CRS class) [side 2], 1979 May 9; 1 (Box 37)
- Topical files
  Topical files contain material relating to the Rudolph building collected by Smith but not directly related to his manuscript. Construction-related files contain notes indicating that they were borrowed from Rudolph's office and never returned.
  - Architects and architecture, printed ephemera, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - George B. H. Macomber Company, correspondence and other construction-related materials, 1960-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Man-environment relations and design research, printed ephemera and correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mechanical engineering for the Art and Architecture Building, correspondence, transmittal sheets, and drawings, 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Site information for the Art and Architecture Building, correspondence, reports, and photographs, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Structural engineering for the Art and Architecture Building, correspondence and transmittal sheets, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Yale School of Art and Architecture alumni questionnaire, correspondence, notes, and questionnaire drafts, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)